It's all about... ME!
The Emperor's New Groove is a adventure, animation,
comedy film directed by Mark Dindal.
Emperor Kuzco is turned into a llama by his ex-administrator Yzma, and must now regain his
throne and his human form with the help of Pacha, a gentle llama herder.
Kuzco (voice), played by David Spade.
Pacha (voice), played by John Goodman.
Yzma (voice), played by Eartha Kitt.
Kronk (voice), played by Patrick Warburton.
Chicha (voice), played by Wendie Malick.
Chaca (voice), played by Kellyann Kelso.
The Emperor's New Groove is a 2000 American animated comedy
film produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation.
It was directed by Mark Dindal and written by David Reynolds, based
on a story conceived by Dindal and Chris Williams.
The film stars David Spade, John Goodman, Eartha Kitt,
Patrick Warburton, and Wendie Malick.
Inspired by ancient Peruvian culture and set in an Incan empire, The Emperor's New Groove follows Emperor Kuzco (voiced by Spade), who is
accidentally transformed into a llama by his treacherous ex-advisor, Yzma (Kitt), and her dimwitted henchman Kronk (Warburton).
For the emperor to change back into a human, he entrusts a village leader, Pacha (Goodman), to
escort him back to the palace before Yzma can track them down and finish him off.
Development of The Emperor's New Groove began in 1994 when the film was
conceived as a musical epic titled Kingdom of the Sun.
Following his directorial debut with The Lion King (1994), Roger Allers
recruited English musician Sting to compose several songs for the film.
Because of the underwhelming box-office performances of Pocahontas (1995) and The Hunchback of
Notre Dame (1996), Dindal was brought in as co-director to make the film more comedic.
Because of poor test screenings, creative differences with Dindal, and production falling behind schedule, Allers departed,
and the film became a lighthearted comedy in the vein of a Chuck Jones cartoon instead of a dramatic musical.
A documentary, The Sweatbox (2002), details the production troubles that The
Emperor's New Groove endured during its six years of development.
The Emperor's New Groove premiered at the El Capitan Theatre in Los Angeles on December 10, 2000, and was released in
theaters by Buena Vista Pictures Distribution under the Walt Disney Pictures banner on December 15, 2000.
It received generally positive reviews from critics but underperformed at the box office compared to
Disney films released in the 1990s, grossing $169.5 million on a $100-million budget.
However, the film found larger success when it was released for home
media, and became the best-selling home video release of 2001.
In the years since its release, The Emperor's New Groove
has garnered a cult following among fans.
It was nominated for an Academy Award for Best Original Song for the song "My Funny Friend and Me",
performed by Sting; that award went to "Things Have Changed" by Bob Dylan from Wonder Boys.
A direct-to-video spin-off sequel, Kronk's New Groove, was released on December 13, 2005, and an animated
television series, The Emperor's New School, aired on the Disney Channel from 2006 to 2008.
The film explores themes of central and south
america, kingdom, birthday, peru, emperor.
The tone is lighthearted.